Guide to the William Allen Haynes papers, 1901-1953 MS 268
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
William Allen Haynes papers
1901-1953
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Haynes, William Allen
MS 268
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Over one half of the collection documents cattle ranching, oil prospecting, and banking in Texas, as well as personal and family life during the Great Depression. The William Allen Haynes collection offers a view of living conditions of a prosperous Central Texas rancher and entrepreneur as well as providing information on conditions in Texas in the first part of the 19th century.
Biographical Sketch
William Allen Haynes (1873-1953?), a native of Bell County, Texas, came from ranching stock. He carried on the family tradition and by the turn of the century was an established rancher. As oil became increasingly lucrative adjunct to ranching, Haynes together with his brother Robert branched out into oil well drilling and leasing oil lands. Haynes, like most ranchers, suffered ups and downs of the cattle market, from difficulties with transporting his cattle, and from the vagaries of weather. Despite these problems, he managed to stay solvent and even make money during the 1920's. One reason for his solvency was that he was never simply a rancher, but derived additional income from oil and investments in real estate. In 1928 Haynes was named a director of the struggling First National Bank of Killeen, and he became president of the bank just in time for the Great Depression. His Bank limped along through the early 1930's as Haynes and the other officers and directors of the bank reduced capitalization and discussed possible liquidation. About 1935 Haynes left banking and focused his energies on ranching and land speculation.
As he grew older, the scope of his activities became increasingly limited, but he maintained an active interest in ranching well into his 70's. Haynes' life was not strictly business however. He was interested in politics and although never serving in an elected position, he often acted as an election judge in his precinct or campaigned for the Democratic Party. Among his political friends were Miriam and Jim Ferguson who both served as Governor of Texas. Parrie and Allen apparently did not have children, but they were very close to their nieces and nephews. Haynes also provided a guiding hand and monetary support for his brothers who were never quite the businessman he was. In later life, as Haynes suffered from sickness and various ailments his familial loyalty paid off, as his family took care of him in his weakened state. In 1952 his last letter was received and in 1959 his collection was donated to Rice University. His actual death occurred at some point between 1952 and 1959.
Scope and Contents
Over one half of the collection documents cattle ranching, oil prospecting, and banking in Texas) as well as personal and family life during the Great Depression. The William Allen Haynes collection offers a view of living conditions of a prosperous Central Texas rancher and entrepreneur as well as providing information on conditions in Texas in the first part of the 19th century. Haynes corresponds with his wife Parrie and family. Of additional interest are the letters which describe the Great Depression years and the letters commenting on politics or seeking Haynes' endorsement. Among the most noteworthy of the political letters are those dealing with James and Miriam Ferguson who also appear in the business letters.
Restrictions on Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth White, 1959.
Index Terms
Subjects
Cattle; Ranches; Banks and banking; Petroleum industry and trade; Great Depression; Business; Ranches and ranching
Document Types
clippings (information artifacts); corrrespondence
Subjects (Persons)
Ferguson, Miriam Amanda; Haynes, Parrie; Haynes, William Allen
- Series I: Business and Legal Documents, 1901-1949, 72326
  Scope and Contents note
  William Allen Haynes was an inveterate collector, saving everything from cattle bulletins to the dietary cure for gonorrhea. From 1901-1917 Haynes was primarily interested in ranching, and his papers proved considerable information on range conditions in central Texas, the cattle markets in Ft. Worth, and his efforts to build up and maintain his ranch through the use of numerous loans and mortgages.
  About 1918 Haynes obtained an interest in the Leon Valley Oil Company, and for the next few years he received extensive correspondence from his brother Robert on the ups and downs of the oil business. From 1919 to about 1935, Haynes' business papers cover a much wider spectrum than in previous years. Besides ranching and oil, the papers deal with land speculation, litigation concerning land titles, and banking. Of special interest in the papers is the correspondence concerning Haynes' efforts to keep the troubled First National Bank of Killeen open. From 1929 to 1935 Haynes served as the president of this bank, and corresponded with prominent Texas bankers as well as Governor Miriam and Jim Ferguson.
  The papers for 1935 to 1952 show a decline in Haynes' business activity. The primary importance of this segment of the collection is the information it gives on the cattle market in Fort Worth, Kansas, Missouri, Oklahoma, and Illinois. Besides business records the Haynes collection contains personal bank records, private correspondence and material pertaining to Bell County Politics from1914 to 1922.
  Typical contents: Court Summons, Real Estate Advertisements, Bank Loan Application and General Correspondence, Receipts for Various Business Purchases, Bail Bonds, Jury Summons, Official Complaint Forms, Criminal Subpoena Forms, Livestock Manuals, Farmer's Bulletins and Advertisements, Life Insurance Forms, Political Messages, Bank Deposit Slips, Tax Receipts, Warrant of Arrest Form.
  - 1901-1915, 72348 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Distinctive Documents: "Rid-O-Fat" weight loss supplement advertisement, Medicated Livestock Salt advertisement, Various automotive parts advertisements
  - 1915, 72347 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Distinctive Documents: Freight Bill for transportation of cattle, Receipt for the sale of cattle, Bank collection notice
  - 1916, 72346 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Distinctive Documents: Stock Company Correspondence, Temple Daily Telegram subscription notice, Livestock Contract, Mortgage Forms, Diamond Tire Advertisement with two steel nails to test puncture resistant tires
  - 1917, 72345 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1918, 72344 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Distinctive Documents: Automobile Tire Caps Advertisements
  - 1919, 72343 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Distinctive Documents: Oil Stock and Land Advertisements
  - 1920, 72342 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Distinctive Documents: Cattle Registration Certificate, Army Auction Notice, Furniture Sale Notice,
  - 1921, 72341 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Distinctive Documents: Chiropractor's Business Card, Membership Card to the United States Live Stock Association
  - 1922, 72340 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Distinctive Documents: Law Suit Correspondence, Holland's Magazine of the South, Lumber Company Receipt, Shaving Cream Receipt, Cotton Price Index and History from 1829-1922
  - 1923, 72339 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Distinctive Documents: Cotton Price Index and History from 1829-1922, Tickets to Central Texas Fair
  - 1924, 72338 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Distinctive Documents: Campaign Letter For R.H. Buck for Chief Justice of Supreme Court of Texas, List of School Lands coming to Market as of September 1, 1924, Receipt for a Hat
  - 1925, 72337 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Distinctive Documents: Surgical Appliances Magazine, Warranty Deed
  - 1926, 72336 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Distinctive Documents: Information Booklet regarding Milk Goats and Goat Milk, Ray Montieth for County Clerk, Poultry and Stock Show
  - 1927, 72335 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Distinctive Documents: Poll Tax Receipt, Taxidermy Advertisement, Traveller's Insurance Document, Scott and White Hospital Documents, Women's Shoes Magazine
  - 1928, 72334 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Distinctive Documents: Rural Telephone Company Check, Political Discourse on Tariffs in a telegram
  - 1929, 72333 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1930, 72332 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Distinctive Documents: Ford manual
  - 1931, 72331 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1932, 72330 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Distinctive Documents: Poll Tax Receipt, Temperance Movement Document
  - 1933, 72329 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Distinctive Documents: Tax Redemption, Letter from Governor Miriam Ferguson regarding Banks buying relief bonds
  - 1934, 72328 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Distinctive Documents: Banker Lobbyist Group letter to W.A. Haynes, Letter from a Texas Congressman regarding Civil Service Exam
  - 1936-1949, 72327 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    Distinctive Documents: Texas Banker's Association official guest list.
- Series II: Personal records, 1910-1952, 72323
  The personal letters received by Haynes and his wife Parrie are among the most interesting portions of the collection. These letters from family and friends give an authentic account of the condition of rancher in Central Texas in the first half of the 19th century. Of particular interest are the letters which describe the Great Depression years and the letters commenting on politics or seeking Haynes' endorsement. Among the most noteworthy of the political letters are those dealing with James and Miriam Ferguson who also appear in the business letters.
  - Personal banking records, 1910-1940; 72325 (Box 2, Folder 5-9)
    Contents: Personal Checks and other monetary records demonstrating his financial situation year to year. Haynes kept practically every canceled check, bank statement, and note payment receipt he ever received, and taken into consideration together give a fairly accurate gauge of his financial situation in any particular year.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1910-1952; 72324 (Box 2, Folder 10-14)
    Contents: Marriage Invitations, Commencement Invitations, Postcards, Letter from Soldier, Personal Finance Records, Personal Letters regarding W.A. Haynes and Family
- Series III: Politics, n.d., 72321
  - Politics, 72322 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Contents: Civil Vote Tally on the Prohibition of Beer, Civil Vote Tally on the Prohibition of Pool Halls, Civil Vote Tally on Prohibition of Alcohol, Farm Mortgages, Letters addressed to W.A. Haynes regarding his position as overseer of general and special election